all right welcome
everyone it's cohort 6 and our second
discussion of chapter one so Andrew and
Ali thanks for facilitating
just take it from here wherever you want
to pick
up Andrew would you mind taking the lead
on this one
sure yeah so I know um yeah absolutely
so welcome cohort 6 this is week two
that we're spending on chapter one of
the
textbook um I'm not sure what was
discussed at the last meeting but I
thought it might be worthwhile for some
of the folks who are unable to attend
the morning meetings to maybe just
quickly move through um the sections of
the
textbook
um just to quickly get a bit of a recap
or
overview
um yeah the overview we begin with a
nice brief
introduction um describing what's going
to be happening in this chapter we
already get off the bat that active
inference is a normative perspective
it's starting from first
principles um move on to section
1.2 get some quick explanations
regarding the relationships between
things like actions and sensory
observations specifically that living
organisms can only maintain their bodily
Integrity by exerting adaptive control
over the action perception Loop this
means acting to solicit sensory
observations that either correspond to
desired outcomes or goals such as the
sensations that accompany secure
nutrients and shelter for simple
organisms or friends in jobs for more
complex ones or help in making sense of
the
world um this is carried out through
there's a rather recursive nature to
this cycle of action uh perception
Loops um also whenever we move on to
looking at more complex organisms
there's the assumption that
organisms can increasingly use like more
complex adaptive strategies to adjust to
their
environment um section 1.3 still more on
um first principles get an introduction
to this uh this kind of I don't want to
call it ad hoc because I think these
conversations have been had before but
it's a a little light-hearted I suppose
this meets versus
scruffy's uh division that's main right
and
so
um scruffies being like these are folks
who will approach these kinds of
problems but maybe from within their
particular field or
subfield um they don't want
to um you know forego any kind of kind
of
idiocy
idiosyncrasies or specificities to their
object of study um so maybe you know not
so quick to jump to some kind of broader
unifying
framework um to analyze things whenever
you know you might let go of some of the
specific the problem you're looking at
um you anthropologists will have
disagreements with sociologists and so
on about what what defines like a
society or or a culture or otherwise um
nonetheless meats are those who do seek
unification Beyond heterogeneity of
brain and mind phenomena and that is the
perspective that active in for instincts
it does in fact attempt a kind of
unified framework at looking at diverse
uh scenarios and organisms ranging from
human beings and entire cultures uh who
are operating at different time scales
of the way at fast time scales of like
what they're immediately observing and
perceiving um all the way up to slower
time scales of like planning
learning um organizing with a group
development of Institutions and so on
um section 1.4 gives us a good overview
kind of structure of the
book
um
1.4.1 active inference in theory we get
more about surprise
minimization um we're also introduced to
variational free energy in the next
paragraph there um they keep it short in
describing why we might look at
variational free energy as opposed to
surprise which seems like a much more
intuitive concept um for one to be
surprised at unexpected uh phenomena or
observations or incoming um sensory
signals um but the the to put it quickly
variational free energy is basically an
upper bound ons surprisal that is done
because
computationally um we find this issue of
intractability in computation when
whenever you break down the math you
find like oh in order to actually
precisely compute surprisal you would
need something like an entire history of
an organism's like memory every
observation it's come across every
potential in state it would estimate and
you can imagine that the the the the
mathematics to that the kind of formula
that would be involved in that would be
um just untenable from a computational
perspective and you can imagine the same
thing for an actual human brain um and
making snap judgments based on its
entire history of what it's learned and
so on so variational free energy is is
very important in order to overcome this
kind of intractability problem
everything is somewhat approximate with
the goal being to minimize free energy
as much as you can such as surprises
also minimized as much as possible there
will be much more on that in the
textbook we're only in chapter one um so
stepping forward from that um we do have
this nice figure
1.2 which describes um how to reach
active inference from two different
routes uh the low road and the high road
we can say that the low road is kind of
the the how of active inference how an
organism maintains its own Integrity um
just before we started this meeting
there were certain uh mentions of autop
pois and so on like this is the how and
and so it it relies heavily upon basis
theorem uh we work up to generative
models and using bases theorem in order
to find relationships between different
variables within the model um and so
that's kind of the mechanics it's the
how but from The High Road alternatively
we get this is where things become a
little bit more of aose uh which is that
this is what and why organisms are doing
what they're doing as far as their
behavior goes and attempting to explain
like what is happening here um they're
minimizing free energy so we begin with
the free energy principle right so we so
then we can start understand living
organisms or other kinds of systems that
we attempt to model using these kinds of
tools on the one hand they're trying to
minimize free energy on the other hand
how are they doing it they're doing it
through something like Basi and
statistics mechanics
um we'll get much more on on both of
those roads to active inference in
chapters 2 and three Each of which are
dedicated to one route uh one route
each following that learn that yourself
when we look at the structure of the
book as it's described from there um to
keep it a little bit shorter um I'll
just say the the first half of the book
is um predominantly dedicated to a lot
of the more theore iCal aspects of
active inference um there will be
explanation of other aspects such as the
the mathematics involved although you'll
find much more on the details of that
math in the appendix um the active
inference Institute also um if you view
the Koda you'll find like references to
the maths um you'll see that there's an
ongoing project right now and it's being
streamed regarding the mathematics of of
active inference so there are plenty of
resources outside of this textbook um
for those who are more interested or or
feel like they're not getting a
sufficient amount of explanation from
the
textbook
um and then we'll also later in this
first part of the book we'll also get
references to uh the kind of the more
neurobiological aspects of the theory of
course it was um largely initially
devised by Carl friston as a
neuroscientist um
a neurobiologist and so the all of this
is heavily based within preceding work
and looking at how to understand the
mind and the Brain
um so with that
said I think beyond that we'll we you
know key words include active inference
is of process Theory we're looking at
different kinds of models discret and
continuous
models we're getting references to yeah
just a variety of things that this is
connected to Hybrid models um I think
that might be fair enough we're trying
to introduce the the chapter we're
already nearly a quarter of the way
through so
um so I'd like to ask if there's any are
there any questions that anyone has
about the textbook or anything that
they've kind of been chewing on for some
time you'd like to
discuss um so can surprise be seen as
the difference between expected
observations and actual
observations yeah I'm sorry I missed
just the first couple words of what you
said could you repeat that for me please
yeah um so so I was asking um can
surprise be seen as the difference
between expected observations and actual
observations that's right so so active
inference kind of relies upon this um
idea that you can think about it as um
like a like a set point for example um
in in control theory or or looking at a
thermostat right so you set the
thermostat to a particular temperature
um there's a signal that's being read
about the temperature in the room um
here's what you want the temperature to
be
here is what it actually is um and then
the idea is you'd want a heating or
cooling system that could then take
action here to bring the the temperature
that it's reading in line with the
expected set point temperature that you
want um and you can quickly see like
yeah you're you're minimizing the
difference between expected and actual
it's a kind of classic machine learning
persp perspective or or or otherwise um
yeah that you'd be effectively
minimizing
surprise um in that
sense but mathema Ma sorry
mathematically it's easier to minimize
variational freey than it is to try and
minimize the area directly right that's
right y the textbook will get much more
into that but it's it's that itself is
also very much based upon mathematics
it's not a arbitrary decisions so but it
it has to do with Jensen's
inequality um the idea that um basically
a particular quantity is always
necessarily greater than or equal to
another one given certain conditions and
so that's how we end up there
um thank
you I ask something uh sorry can you
hear me
yes yes uh i u a lot of things hinge on
the generative model that an agent or an
organism has and I I often wonder it
like and and yeah when I read further in
the book then I see that the generative
model is considered given somehow you
you you seem to you you seem it's
considered to that you have access to it
uh so then I wonder where does that
model come from who chooses what model
is there uh the parameters seem to be
updated through message passing and that
kind of uh stuff but uh uh the model
itself um it's the the P and not the Q
but where where does
it yeah where does it come from or or
how should one think about
that
before I give an answer I was just
wondering if anyone else um wants to
chime in on that thought because it is a
big
question it's um I guess uh does the
free under oh I'm sorry people are
raising their hands uh let them go
first yeah
Ali Anna did you have a
question oh yeah but Ali was is gonna go
first he was
first uh okay so what I wanted to
comment
was a bit unrelated to this current
question so Eric would you please uh go
on about what you were talking about
before
thanks oh I I was just going to say
um I think is his like how the model is
updated is is that
um is that really addressed directly by
the free energy principle or is it kind
of like mysterious right
because um it seems like uh you kept on
you keep on getting this phrasing from
uh friston like this is how a an
organism has to behave if you know um so
uh um I don't know coming from a
neuroscience perspective I'm not sure we
quite understand how it
works but we could see that the brain
seems to be doing it
something like
this I I don't know if that's a good
answer
but yeah know that that makes a lot of
sense I mean it's so to I mean come at
to come at any kind of and this is just
me speaking but to come at any kind of
phenomena I presume you have to you know
you start with some kind of framework
where you attempt to like kind of
structure things and then and then as
far as living organisms and the behavior
goes yeah it's I mean all of this is
sort of um you know the map is not the
the territory we're just attempting to
understand the organisms right and so
active inference is like attempting to
provide that so the just to comment on
how you phrased it as like it's as if uh
it is undertaking free energy
minimization I think that's a just fine
way of saying it um so as far as yeah
defining a gener generative model I
suppose it depends on what kind of
perspective you want to take so there
are many people at the Institute who are
more focused on the modeling and and the
programming right and so they want to
construct like a model themselves U
maybe it's to simulate something like an
agent it's an environment um in that
case yeah you're kind of you would want
to rely upon things like domain
knowledge in in conjunction with with a
lot of the principles of active
inference and basing mechanics which as
we mentioned earlier is kind of the low
road to active inference um that's
already your starting point you you
already assume that the agent is
attempting to minimize free energy and
it's doing it through a variety of
principles all related back to basis
theorem um so that that's kind of the
the top- down normative framework that's
being used here
and then from there it's sort of up to
you as far as how you want to continue
constructing that model right so if if
if if there's certain actions that are
available to the model or not that it
can take um what are the different kinds
of states it it already expects to see
what are the the priors this this is the
kind of language that we'll get more
deeply into is the the textbook you know
as we continue reading through the
chapters
um from another perspective if you're
not modeling but rather just kind of
going through the theory here I mean
it's there can be bigger philosophical
questions about um the structure of an
agent why it is the way it is um I think
that there are many people who study
active inference who kind of follow the
line of of something along the lines of
natural selection or perhaps more
nuanced um versions of that
theory uh you know since its initial
conception and so I don't want to say
too much here but has that at all been
helpful in in trying to answer the
initial question
yours yeah I I see that this is uh this
is not not an easy question and not uh
but I I understand that there is for a
modeler there is
a lot of room
for uh you say
creative filling in of the structure of
the model at least it seems uh while um
yeah if I get you right then it's not
something that is necessarily derived
from uh a
normative point of view or
something yeah I mean of of course like
with any kind of scholarly pursued I
mean whenever there's already work
that's been done whenever there's
already secondary literature to draw
from and so on of course folks will
build upon one another's models and test
things out and oftentimes you'll
construct one model and then eventually
realize like it's Its Behavior despite
the fact that it's minimizing free
energy the way you might have set up the
variables in the model like the behavior
at elicits doesn't actually match any
kind of real world phenomena that you're
actually you might be attempting to
simulate for example um in that case
it's it can be a trial and error process
um it can involve discovering something
that you didn't expect to to find when
you realize oh there's a missing
variable here um yeah those are many of
the
general uh trials and erors of of model
construction I suppose um yeah
thank
you um Anna I did want to come back
around to you yeah
um okay so actually my
[Music]
question um is relevant to the previous
question I think um so on page six of
the book um there's you know this
sentence that I'm going to read it says
active inference is a normative
framework to characterize Bas optimal
behavior and cognition in living
organisms and so I was wondering if you
could
um give us
a an overview or
some um ideas to start thinking
around the you know what what does a
basian model
optimize and um so because that's the
basian optimization is a tool that
allows us to think about the
world and so I'm curious about things
things like what what utilities
are uh optimized in basian
models uh is that are the utilities um
specific
to the phenomena that you're working
with um
and and if you could connect and discuss
you know the utility to the probability
functions that are used in basian stats
statistics so again this time I do want
to open the floor if anyone has any any
thoughts on on this or otherwise um to
maybe see if we can get into this um
this question that an's posed
go
foron oh well I I had my hand raised
from to ask an independent thing but I
guess like in terms of um I can try to
take a stab at this one um so I would I
would phrase it as beian models don't on
their own optimize for anything but the
model itself States the relationship
between variable
that is assumed and under those
assumptions one can in light of new
evidence um Express a posterior
distribution which describes one's
beliefs and I think classically that's
like fully separate from how we think
about utility uh utility functions and
sort of given my posterior distribution
about the world I can then choose to act
depending on what my my preferences
are
can you can you um add to your example
like
uh a you some you know what what is the
currency that's being
optimized it just I understand that the
modeler decides what currency is being
optimized So when you
say when you're talking about
beliefs updating beliefs and so on what
are we optimizing
there you know so how do we
translate uh the you know the natur the
natural
language um updating
beliefs what does that look like in a in
a in a model and
can so one one way that I would anyone
feel pry derail to derail me on this uh
one way that I think about um ban
updating and and I think like the
currency that that's at play here is uh
units of surprise so bits or Nats right
and I think like the the the textbook
doesn't really talk about this I feel
like other sources are better about like
grounding bits or kns as like a unit for
surprise but like if you were to have a
lot of observations from a distribution
and you want to communicate those to
some other party efficiently um
literally how many bits do you need per
per observation um that's the kind of
thing that uh is reduced as your model
of the source of the data is improved so
if you're if you're constantly surprised
then you're going to take more bits per
observation to communicate what you're
observing and if your model is pretty
well explaining what you're seeing then
you'll need many fewer bits per
observation to to report or communic
um and I guess maybe communication comes
like loaded with some expectations of
like between agents but I think also
that can be between components within an
agent in in some cases but yeah that
bits or kns are like actually an
expression of uh perplexity surprise um
on average I suppose um that can be uh
reduced by updating
appropriately thank
you
okay and I I do want to add to that to
um I think it was well said Erin in
pointing to yeah it's it's frequently
understated like what the units of
measurement here are whenever we're
looking at something like surprisal um
that said if we want to look at it in
terms of active inference I mean some
some things that you're going to see are
are commonalities throughout the
textbook is we're going to be looking at
particular variables and so um we're
going to be looking at priors which can
be viewed as something like prior
predictions what you think is going to
happen um or or is happening um I.E your
hidden state that you're estimating and
then you'll have sensory observations
right which is new information that's
coming in um this is where we get into
things like predictive coding or
processing at least uh where there is a
continuous process of um comparison
between what information you're getting
versus what you thought would happen
this kind of hearkens back a little bit
to the general idea of you know here's
the ex expected observations here's the
actual ones like the thermostat examples
and it's through kind of starting with
bases theorem as a sort of foundation
like that's the how of of reducing
surprise right so um given some new
information exactly I mean I don't want
to rehash what Aaron said because I
think you put it much more eloquently
than what I'm prepared to but um yeah
it's to
um to minimize surprise via uh taking in
new information updating what you
thought you knew before suddenly your
predictions perhaps come more into line
with what you see out in the environment
it's much more complex than that
depending on the situation
but um that's an attempt at getting
closer to describing you know here's
what we're doing whatever War minimizing
surprise um Erin I do uh you've had your
hand up for some time so I'd like to
allow you to speak on on your original
question yeah okay so one thing that I
struggle to get my head around here is
the generative model um is supposed to
generate like all of your sensory data
or is like supposed to like go all the
way out to like you know the the margins
of the mark blanket or whatever the
things that are coming in from the
exterior World um and how plausible is
that really like there's lots of cases
where you can see a complicated
situation and not be able to predict
most of it um and a lot of the things
that the details that may be surprising
possibly aren't going to be relevant to
any action uh you know you look at um a
whole bunch of birds flocking together
you don't know where any particular one
of them is but it kind of doesn't matter
uh if you look at a TV screen with a
bunch of static you can't predict what
color any pixel is going to be in the
next millisec but you can predict like
derived features about a scenario um and
so I'm wondering sort of there should be
some intermediate layer uh that is more
relevant for our generative model to
populate than like the actual sense data
coming
in
does anyone have any thoughts on
that uh actually this is uh directly
relevant to John verve's relevance
realization uh because um in the in that
framework uh it's
not it's not possible for an organism to
encode every single bit of information
about its
environment uh I mean with uh sufficient
Precision so uh it needs to only encode
uh only the information uh which is
relevant uh relevant uh to the uh
situation uh which it's dealing uh with
with currently so um one way to do that
is to uh is to encode those information
probabilistically instead of
deterministically because uh in
uh our traditional algorithmic
formulation of cognitivism for example
uh we deal with with well-defined
situation in which the parameters are
pretty much clearcut clearcut and we can
encode them uh with u arbitrary
Precision if you want but uh in one of
the selling points of predictive
processing Frameworks is that uh it's
not necessary
to uh to encode those information with
any uh kind of precision at all you can
even start from uh I mean in principle
you can start from a from an arbitrary
Precision from an arbitrary distribution
and then uh and then move your way uh
in in a in an optimization scenario uh
so for in for instance you can do a
gradient descent on the VF landscape and
reach uh the extrema or the minimum uh
of the variation of free energy and uh
that's uh one of the one of the
fundamental differences between uh
active inference or predictive uh
processing
Frameworks uh from the other traditional
uh cognitivist uh Frameworks
because uh as this recent uh paper
naturalized in relevance realization
shows
uh in real world real world
situations cognition might be
fundamentally incomp uncomputable so but
um we can uh I mean get around uh this
obstacle by uh somehow uh encoding uh
that generative model
probabilistically uh and only encode the
information that are relevant uh to us
yeah I think there there have been
arguments that have been made
especially just a brief tangent that
that you know living organism living
organisms who who necessarily like have
um kind of metabolic um rules to to keep
in place and you know home homeostasis
to maintain tendency to we we can view
this as one potential explanation for
something like only paying attention to
what is surprising and meanwhile trying
to kind of put on the back end all the
processes involved in um you know
determining like what is the new
information here and what is not the new
information do we need to know the
position of every single seagull in the
flock as it moves by to be able to
comprehend that this is a flock of
sequels right um it you know that I I
think it just it kind of hits on the
aspect of of active inference but it
doesn't even necessarily have to be
active inference like the importance of
something like a having a variational
dynamic that allows for things like
dimensionality reduction and increase
from there compressing information and
um just kind of keeping things a little
bit more
efficient um in any case um I would like
to give others a chance to ask questions
uh
how apologies if
I um yeah thanks so that um yes so I
guess you know I guess coming from
machine learning as well I I try to I
guess compartmentalize my my learning
here and um you does active influence in
influence news um new networks gradient
descent um and you like back
publication or is it like a just you
know
different I'll give a quick answer to
this there's an
essential analytical form that is just
matrix multiplication so what we see in
the textbook is just matrix
multiplication how however a lot of the
modern uh examples have used neural
networks as kind of like plug-and play
for different things like instead of a
massive a matrix you can have a neural
network and there's also deeper
theoretical Connections in live stream
51 with tuya isura this discusses the
monotonic relationship between the
variational free energy and the neural
network uh loss function and then
live stream 52 or like anything with
Lance D Costa is super informative about
how accelerated optimization methods are
used with variational free energy some
of which are um generally accessible to
any variational method others are
especially enabled by act in for
FP interesting so it can use new
networks but it it doesn't need to
exactly
oh
okay
um oh I had a question but yeah I've
lost
it um yeah thanks for the answer by the
way uh
Thomas yeah I mean just kind I want to
build on some of the questions and
looking for examples on that generative
model point I remember the the frisen
article on aesthetic experience uh Order
and Chaos there's a note in it about the
nature of absences so there's like
visuals basically of a square with a
piece cut off and there's a comment in
the caption they talked about absen are
meaningful as obstacles or prediction
error so I think that's really
interesting because that's pointing out
that a kind of absence um it's almost
like where's the grounding like where's
the gender of mod come from it seems to
be and that relates to the other parts
of that essay where he talks about this
kind of epistemic promise that our we're
using we engage in AR the experiences
because there's been a promise that
we're going to get some kind of payoff
of epistemic basically Clarity or
resolution of some kind um there's a lot
more Nuance in that but just I want to
point that just to kind of build on this
point where is this Jen of model gr
bottom up thing coming from absences or
lacks basically that are pointing out
that that's a kind of course basically
either there's an objective you're
trying to achieve that's being hindered
so there's an obstacle in that mode or
there's a basically a difference between
the the prediction model in your head
versus the reality of interfacing with
it um I think that's interest that's
kind of that was an interesting just
building point on where potentially a
generative model comes from um also just
other idea like where I'm thinking in my
head I was looking reading this piece
and where this comes from concretely as
an example it's like you got a gallon of
milk in the fridge you think it's full
you're not paying attention so you
recruit way too much energy boom and you
pull you You Yank it out with way more
Force than expected
uh that difference basically is a
surprise I mean that's why I'm thinking
as a concrete example of um so in that
case what's the currency being
manipulated years is calories basically
to bur basically to recruit the energy
required for the muscles to contract and
move on that example those things I
wanted to
share yeah no good good points than for
sharing those I mean yeah again with the
you know expecting a much
you know jug of of milk is another very
quick intuitive example of you know
here's the difference between what you
predict is is currently going on the
hidden state of the world like I have a
full jug of milk um what actually
happens there's much less uh milk in
there you know you end up like yanking
it out way too quickly there's excessive
metabolic like expenditure there um
those are all ways of for sure thinking
about it and and you know uh at some
point in the textbook we'll see
explanations of things like uh Arc
reflexes um and
proprioception where uh it'll describe
things like like for example you can
move on from that example you gave to
imagining like the arm will adjust right
like well we hope it does anyway like
the arm will not just immediately fling
out it will like maybe halfway through a
quarter of the way through the movement
start to pick up like oh this is
actually not heavy enough to justify
this amount of force there'll be some
kind of change in the action sequence
right like suddenly you're not hopefully
you're no longer G to fling
it sorry it's kind of a silly example
isn't it but um but you see the point
it's like error correction right so so
there's what you expect there's what's
you're actually observing and then
there's an um action can then be used to
try and correct for that error um which
ultimately uh presumably minimizes free
energy along the way
um
Eric um yes I was just gonna also add um
to the question raised earlier that
maybe part of the answer to the question
about whether um the model really has to
um model every Century detail is just
that there's there 's actually many
models that are working together um in
in in an organic system so um they don't
all have to model
everything um and uh like if I
understand uh B's take um I think he
believes that like the um task task
centered Network and the default mode
Network which kind of take turns right
when you're um when you're doing various
activities that you know the um the uh
default default mode network is
basically aspectual ising different
things in the world and
um like offering them up to the um task
Focus Network which is selecting some of
them um and that they're constantly
mutually modeling each other so that the
organism can move through a salience
landscape but um you know um we tend to
reduce organisms you know being
conscious creatures we tend to think of
the model as oh it's me the conscious me
right but there's all these um my
understanding is that there's all these
um generative models right working
beneath my
Consciousness um allowing some things to
appear in others you know um so maybe
that's part of um how it works
efficiently because there's many
different
models hopefully that's
coherent yeah know it makes a lot of
sense to me and I I think um you know
this where we start to see a little bit
more relationship with um yeah as you
described raiki theories as well as you
know if anyone's familiar with like
Global workspace Theory basically this
the idea that you can have a kind of uh
like multiple systems within a single
system or nested systems and um we're
already in chapter one briefly
introduced to the idea of a marov
blanket but um as the textbook continues
there'll be some more regarding Markov
blankets and what what separates statist
in this sense stat also statistically
separates a system from another system
and then also recognizing that there can
be like nested systems within systems or
systems who appear to be working
cooperatively together and so in the
context of like a human being um we only
need a like a you know what's a quick
example someone who uh is a cigarette
smoker or something right like someone
who on the one hand like and and decides
to quit that's sorry I'll keep it more
brief than that um someone who decides
they want to quit like
top level hierarchical like higher order
decision I want to quit I want to be
done with this um this is good like
that's what I want to do that's a higher
order decision on the other hand uh you
know give them you know roughly 15
minutes and they start experiencing a
craving and as that time continues we
have you know withdrawal symptoms and so
on um suddenly the person will become
potentially more ambivalent um
there are different systems in the body
that are expecting that nicotine uh to
to come in right um and
so you can have like multiple systems
within a single human being or a single
system that are potentially in conflict
with one another cooperating with one
another um it's really about what is the
phenomena you're interested in whenever
it comes to active inference and
applying it as a framework what is the
what is the system of for you and and
you have to decide like what defines
those boundaries like what Behavior am I
expecting to see what system am I trying
to to um simulate
here what potential nested systems are
within that broader system um so at risk
of over speaking I'll I'll uh give the
floor back but uh no I I think those are
all great questions and uh things to
think about
um
Ali yeah I just wanted to add uh to what
Thomas just mentioned about um I mean uh
the the absence of information uh
because that's exactly uh the premise of
U Terence Deacon's incomplete nature
because uh in his magnumopus he develops
theory of absenti ism and he tries to
somehow uh derive kind Tio Dynamics
based exactly on those uh what he calls
appsential so uh in one of our works
with uh ma and I U which is INF
interaction inference uh we uh we
initially developed an account of the
interaction between the organism and the
environment based on possibility spaces
so uh very briefly any system with a
given State space uh would would have a
form of the possibility space based on
uh the definition or the collection of
uh its Tendencies and capacities and uh
and the structure of this possibility
space can be described uh or defined as
a multiplicity as a delusion uh
multiplicity so by multiplicity uh what
we mean is a nested set of vector Fields
uh which are related uh to each other
hierarchically by symmetry breaking
bifurcations uh and uh which together
they constitute a kind of a collection
of distributions of
attractors um uh which Define each of
the uh their success their subsequent or
embedded levels so in in other words uh
the idea of essentialism is already um
embedded in these uh spaces of
possibility ities or the multiplicities
because those are exactly what
constitute the structure of uh the state
of the space of possibility as uh as the
attractors of the multiplicities so uh
in one of our recent papers we we're
trying to develop uh this connection um
a bit more explicitly and uh yes uh I
agree that um those appsential are uh
quite essential for uh any kind of
representational framework uh or
generative
models so I have a question Ali about
absent
ISM and sure uh yeah
so how can I ask this
um so in Bas in statistics we are
using probability
distributions
to get
at understanding something about
reality um can
you define
entalis in the context of probability
Theory or is it completely
unrelated okay so uh first of all as um
as a side note uh Terrence Deacon
actually uh doesn't use the term abs
essentialism in his book and uh he even
rejects uh this word explicitly but um
in any case in all of the literature
related to incomplete nature they've
used the word absenti ISM so uh it's
pretty much um widely accepted so uh by
absenti ISM he means something that's
not uh physically realized yet or in
other words uh as would call
it it's not actual but a virtual
possibility of uh the system so uh for
instance as a very simple example you
can think of the capacity of a knife uh
to cut to kill or I don't know
to to poke something so uh so yeah all
of these are kind of capacities of the
the of the knife uh which are not always
actualized they reside as uh as its
virtualities uh in its space of
possibilities right and uh the knife may
or may not ever actualize these
virtualities but it uh it doesn't make
it any less real so by appsential
absenti Concepts um or as another Rel
term of Deacon um um intentional
Concepts he means something similar uh
kind of possibility or potentiality uh
which is not actualized or realized yet
uh but uh it is real and it constitute
uh I mean
the uh the D the internal dynamics of
the system uh as um as its potential as
its capacities and
Tendencies so uh I'm not sure if we can
characterize uh absenti ISM in terms of
probabilities because uh although it it
can be
said that some of those
virtualities uh are more probable than
others to be actualized uh but uh but it
needs um a much more rigorous uh work on
that uh to uh to derive these kinds of
probabilistic landscape over those
multiplicities but in any case that
multiplicity exists as a kind of reality
of the system or the agent uh again
whether uh I mean regardless of U
whether it actualizes those
possibilities or virtualities or
not
so
it would would it be incorrect to say
that there are states that are virtually
or have a
potential that they
exist in some virtual representation
somewhere and and that those states are
not uh accessible to us for whatever
reason
for to The Observer at some point in
time but yes to me to me that that
translates let's see I'm trying to see
if I this is making any sense to me that
translates
into in order for me to even think about
that thing that's absent I The Observer
need to have some sense of what what
could possibly what could
possibly be
absent so I as the Observer have to also
have a virtual version of the thing
that's
absent and exactly and would and would
that thing that's
absent not have a probability
distribution so you see uh these
appsential kind of reside uh
in the space of possibility for this the
space of possibility of the system right
uh but uh in order to actualize those
possibilities of course they can be
prioritized based on the probabilities
of U I mean those absenti to be
actualized as I mentioned earlier some
of those
virtualities uh can occur with a higher
frequency than others right uh
but this is this is a very subtle point
and active inference
uh which is to say that uh you see in
recent years I mean uh beginning from
2022 uh there's this uh attempt to
somehow um blur the line between uh The
Observer and The observed by showing a
complete Symmetry and Duality between Fe
and cmap uh which is the constraint
maximum entropy principle right so in
other words uh what the the recent
formalism of active inference or rather
FP shows is this complete Symmetry and
Duality between uh these two perceptions
these two I mean distinctions between
observed and the Observer so uh every
time we uh draw a mark of blanket a
statistical boundary between a system or
between the Observer and The observed it
can basically be treated as a kind of
arbitrary boundary we can uh we can
switch that observed uh and observer
perspective um and uh the formalism uh
will help perfectly so uh um yes there
is this Duality and perfect symmetry
between Observer and observed which is
shown uh formally in recent work by
Dalton Sac divided El and others and
especially from the Viewpoint of
category theoretical perspective it can
be um shown much more
eloquently uh through those um category
theoretical formulation as well such as
the work of um uh Toby SMI and
others thank you appreciate
it
um unfortunately I see we're just about
out of time here it's been we' run
through the the whole hour and for a I
will say for a discussion on chapter one
of a textbook this got rather deep uh
very interesting stuff though very happy
to hear everyone share their their
thoughts and uh
I would you know of course everyone here
is coming from their own distinct
perspective and and interests so I would
say you know if you are coming from a
certain angle certainly don't hesitate
to to ask questions I think that's
what'll well what will kind of pull you
into to active inference a little bit
more quickly in a way that you know is a
little bit more fluent um for a lot of
people because it can be a lot of
material at one time but um thanks Ali
for for Co facilitating and and your
very U your very thorough responses I
always end up learning something new
about uh active inferences history and
and sub theories that makes me want to
read more um and uh thanks everyone else
uh for attending uh per usual there will
be another meeting next week uh we'll be
going over chapter two which is where
we'll get into the low road to active
inference a lot more on basian
statistics and mechanics
um we'll get a maybe a clearer view of
what optimality means or optimal uh
behavior and inference um we'll also get
a couple perspectives on things like uh
different time scales such as inference
at a very quick Moment by moment scale
all the way up to uh planning and agents
who actually have the capacity for
planning their next move or or or
constructing you know goals that will
take a series of steps to carry out not
just taking a breath in the moment
because you need it um Daniel do you
have anything to to add or
announcements no great all right thank
you everyone farewell thanks every
thanks everyone bye